Everybody, Peter Zeihan here, coming to
you from the Canadian Rockies in
Alberta. Just out for a morning stroll.
Uh
today, we're going to do kind of a
public service announcement
question from the Patreon crowd. And
it's do I worry about wild animals when
I'm out backpacking for extended period
of time, specifically bears, because
there have been reports of hundreds of
attacks
uh of bears throughout Japan, especially
northern Japan,
uh this last year, um which I think is
more than what has happened in the
decade previous.
>> [snorts]
>> Uh the short version is no, I don't. And
a couple of big reasons that separate
the North American experience from the
Japanese experience. So, first, the
physical human topography.
In the United States, even in small
towns, you tend to have an urban core
surrounded by a suburban zone surrounded
by an exurban zone, and then outside of
that, ranches and farms.
That's not [snorts] the Japanese
experience. Japan is a very rugged
archipelago, and so in many cases, the
mountains come right down to the small
enclave that is home to the urban zone.
So, the bears are used to being right up
against the edge of human habitation
>> [snorts]
>> even in the best of times.
Second,
uh
>> [gasps]
>> the Japanese physical footprint for
humanity has evolved quite a bit in the
last 30 years as their demographics have
failed. Uh keep in mind that Japan
demographically is the oldest society
right now with the highest proportion of
senior citizens.
And [snorts]
uh the population has been shrinking for
the last 20 years.
And as you age, you live differently.
So, you know, in your 20s, it's all
about hostel vacations. In your 30s,
it's all about single-family homes so
you can raise your kids. In your 60s,
it's all about starting to downsize. And
by the time you hit your 70s and your
80s, which is where the population bulge
in Japan is, you're starting to need to
live closer to one another uh in order
to get services. And so, the elderly
tend to move out of the farms and the
ranches and out of the exurbs and even
out of the suburbs into the city core
where there's a communal living facility
where they can get assistance. And so
what we have seen over the last 20 years
is a steady abandonment
of the outer edges and even kind of the
outer core of a lot of urban zones
throughout Japan.
>> [snorts]
>> Uh and that has left the bears with new
territory to claim. Bears tend to be
pretty territorial even if you relocate
them a couple hundred miles, they're
likely just to run back within a week.
So [snorts and sighs]
in the United States when bears come
across a human settlement, there's
progressively more noise and more
activity and more alien environment with
all these artificial constructions and
above all else humans to scare them
away, human activity whether it's a car
or some guy just yelling at them.
>> [snorts]
>> That doesn't happen in a lot of northern
Japan anymore. This is the part of the
country that has faced the the steepest
demographic crisis, a lot of young
people have relocated to major cities
like Osaka or Tokyo.
And so the outer rim which comes right
up against the mountains has been
abandoned and the bears bit by bit
explore this new zone, claim it as their
own. And so when they do run across a
human, they don't see the human
as an alien environment, they see it as
an intruder and attacks can happen.
Uh
>> [snorts]
>> the bears also have no problem breaking
into a house
uh and there've been plenty of examples
of bears breaking in to find the pet
food and then eating the pet, too.
Uh that just doesn't happen in the
United States. Uh in the United States,
interactions between bears and humans
have usually ended with the bear being
uh scared off. Uh black bear, you
basically make yourself big and loud and
they run off. That doesn't work as well
with an Asian bear. Uh which brings us
to the third thing, uh there's different
species. American black bears are
basically big raccoons, they're
primarily scavengers. Uh that's why they
call them trash pandas in Colorado. So
if you keep your trash in your garage
and you have a locked trash box, you
only put it out the day that it gets
picked up, you're more or less going to
be fine. Oh, yeah. Fun random fact,
black bears love baby diapers. Very
strange.
Anyhow,
the bears in Asia in Japan are called
Asian bears. Different species, a lot
more aggressive.
Making noise, especially in an area that
they don't feel threatened in, is more
likely to trigger an attack than it is
to make them run away.
>> [snorts]
>> Of course, there are
lots of different kinds of bears around
the world. So, for example, the bear you
should worry about in North America is
the grizzly. Their range starts in
Wyoming and works north throughout the
Canadian Rockies.
They're much bigger, they're much more
aggressive. They're still omnivores like
all bears, but they're perfectly capable
of hunting.
If you come across a
grizzly bear in the wild, the best thing
is to stop,
look down and slowly back away and just
hope that it's not interested in you. If
you do get charged, don't make yourself
big and loud, that'll just piss it off.
Don't shoot it with a gun, that'll just
piss it off more. I mean, these things
are half a ton, the small ones. So,
that's not going to stop it all. Your
best bet is bear spray, which is
basically a capsicum spray that stuns
them because they've got really
sensitive eyes and noses.
Like I was saying earlier, the grizzlies
are Wyoming north, so there's actually a
really dense concentration of them right
where I am right now and um
>> [snorts]
>> and I don't have any bear spray on me.
So, you know, maybe maybe this is a good
time to turn around.